Lord, Victor A.; Papers apap318
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Lord, Victor A.
1924-2013
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap318
5 cubic ft.
This collection contains the papers of Victor A. Lord.
Collection X
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2010 and 2013 by Athena V. Lord.
Historical Note
Victor A. Lord, Jr., a native of Schenectady, New York, obtained a law degree from Yale University after serving time overseas in World War II. In 1951 he returned to the Albany area and joined the law firm of McNamee, Lochner, Titus, and Williams. Lord also joined the Junior Chamber of Commerce, which indirectly led to an eye-opening view of Albany's Democratic Machine. His activities with the Chamber introduced him to his future wife, who would also be his partner in promoting social and political change in Albany. Together they became involved with reform groups like the Albany Independence Movement (AIM) and the Citizens United Reform Effort (CURE), both of which were foundations for the Albany Liberal Party. He also worked closely with the Brothers, an organization fighting for racial equality in Albany, NY. Lord and his colleagues worked to end corruption in local and state government, promoting an end to the five-dollar vote, end to racial prejudice, and greater variety of voices in political matters.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Lord's notes, correspondence, speeches, brochures and booklets on matters of social reform, and many fliers, pamphlets, and news clips regarding voting, Albany public schools, urban renewal, race issues, the Albany police and fire departments, and the elections of Dan Button to Congress and John Haith Jr. to local politics.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged in alphabetical order.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Albany, New York; Social Activist; Albany, New York; Correspondence.; Civil Rights; Civil rights--New York (State)
- 3rd Ward City of Albany L.P. Enrollment, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 17th and 18th Wards City of Albany L.P. Enrollment, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Acknowledgment and Awards of Victor Lord, 1989; 2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Albany Civil Rights, 1962-1963; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Albany County, Bolard of Elections Regitrations of Enrollments, 1982; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Albany County Opportunity Incorporated (ACOI), 1966-1967; 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Albany County Resolutions, 1962; 1964; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Albany Democrat Newspaper, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Albany High School, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Albany High School, News Clippings, 1965-1966; 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Albany Independence Movement, 1966-1967; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Albany Independent, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Albany Mirror, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Albany's O'Connell Machine Manuscript by Frank Robinson (1 of 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Albany's O'Connell Machine Manuscript by Frank Robinson (2 of 2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Albany's O'Connell Machine by Frank Robinson, Draft Chapter 14, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- ""Albany Politics, "Amalgam of Sources for Jr. Fri. Paper,", 1924; 1964-1967; 1975; 1981-1984; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Albany Public School #24 Fire Safety, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Albany Public Schools, 1949; 1957; 1960; 1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Albany Public Schools Fact Cards by School Number, 1945-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), 1966; 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- American Labor Party, Personal Notes, 1960-1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Arbor Hill Community Center, 1963; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Binder Notepages, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Board of Education, 1951-1972; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Board of Education, Annual Reports, 1949; 1951-1952; 1954; 1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Board of Community Relations, Bound Report, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Bound C.U.R.E Folder, 1961; 1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Bound Notebooks, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- The Brothers, $5 Vote, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Button, Dan, 1967; Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Campaign for Harriman, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Campaigning, 1963-1964; Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- The Capital District Regional Planning Commission, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Case Regarding: Reverend Smythe, 1967; Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- City Beautification Articles, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- City of Albany, Bound Annual Reports, 1950-1953; 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- City of Albany, Budgets and Finance, 1960-1962; 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Citizens Association for Social Betterment of Arbor Hill (CASBAH), 1962-1963; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Citizens Planning Committee for Albany, 1963; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Citizens United Reform Effort (C.U.R.E.) (1 of 2), 1957-1961; 1975; 1983; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Citizens United Reform Effort (C.U.R.E.) (2 of 2), 1957-1961; 1975; 1983; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Clark Case, 1962; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Cohoes Citizens Committee, 1962-1963; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Committee Assignments Tabbed Folder, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Committee for an Independent Liberal Party, 1984; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Committee to Preserve the Liberal Party, Financial Disclosure Statements, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Construction, 1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Copies of Poll Violation Documents, 1962-1966; 1980-1982; 1984; Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, C.U.R.E, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, General, 1961-1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, Memos, 1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, Notes, 1961; 1964; 1968; 1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Corrrespondence Regarding Education, 1965-1966; 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Coroner, 1961; Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- C.U.R.E., Basic Facts and Recommendations, 1961; Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- C.U.R.E. Organization Personalties, 1961; Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- C.U.R.E. Press Releases and Letters to Editor, 1961; Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Department of Recreation, Reports, 1961; 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Education Articles, 1957; Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Education, Bound Reports and Publications, Albany Centric, 1956-1957; 1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Education, Bound Reports and Publications, National, 1955; 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Education, Conference of Large City Board of Education, Bound Programs, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Education, Development of Human Resources, 1958-1959; 1961-1962; 1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Education, Guidance Counselors, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- "Elections '70's", 1970-1979; Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Election and Voting, 1961; 1972; 1975; 1981; Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Environment, Parks and Recreation, 1966-1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- "Evolution of Governmental…", Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Federal Aid Brochures, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Filofax, 1952-1961 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- FIRE (Completed Work) and Research, 1957-1961; Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Frank Simpson Poem, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
- The Friends of the Brothers, 1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Graduation and Education Demographic Statistics, 1964; 1965; 1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Grand Jury-Five Dollar Vote Buying, 1967; Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Haith Campaign, $5 Election Votes (1 of 2), 1962; Undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Haith Campaign, $5 Election Votes (2 of 2), 1962; Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Haith Campaign, City Treasurer, 1962-1963; Undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Haith, John E. Jr, 1962; 1964; Undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Haith, John- Materials on Community Living and Community Building, 1952-1961; 1963; 1975; Undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Handwritten Notecards, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Handwritten Notes, 1967; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Handwritten Notes about Education, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Housing, 1960-1961; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Housing, Research Work, 1955-1961; Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- The Independent, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Inter-Racial Council, Albany, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Investigations, 1967-1983; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Koch Election and Defamation, Liberal Party, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- League of Women Voters (1 of 2), 1959-1961; 1963-1965; 1969; Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- League of Women Voters (2 of 2), 1959-1961; 1963-1965; 1969; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- League of Women Voters, Ward/ Voter Redistricting, 1964-1965; Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Letters to Athena, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Liberal Party (1 of 2), 1961-1975; 1983-1984; Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Liberal Party (2 of 2), 1961-1975; 1983-1984; Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Liberal Party, Acceptance of Canidacy, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Liberal Party, Appointment of Memberto Fill Vacancies, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Liberal Party, Consent of Substituted Candidate, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Liberal Party Election Supporting Docs, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Liberal Party, Enrollment List, 1967; Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Liberal Party, News Articles, 1978; 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Liberal Party, Petition to Designate Candidate by Ward, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Liberal Party, Receipt of Petition for Candidates, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Library, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Lord and Beatrice Ganeles Against Thomas Donohue, Charles Ryan, Edward Dillon, and William Marrow RE: Election Law and Board of Elections, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Lord and Churches, 1965; Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Lord's Document Regarding Voter Fraud and DA Response, 1966-1967; Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Lord, Victor, General Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Lord, Victor Speeches, 1964; Undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Members of Democratic County Committee, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Mental Health, 1954; 1958-1959; 1965-1966; Undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
- News Articles/Editorials, 1961; 1964; 1966; Undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Newspaper Articles About Elections, 1961; 1977; 1981 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- New York Civil Liberties Union (NYCLU), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- NY State Women's Legislative Forum, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Parent-Teacher Association (PTA) for Albany Public Schools, 1963; 1965-1966; 1967 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Parks and Recreation, 1960; 1961; 1969; Undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Political Buttons (Artifact-box 1)
- Reports, 1964; Undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Republicans, 1970; Undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Research and Subject Files, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Resolutions Adopted at NAACP Meeting, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- The Rosenstock Board, 1972; Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Rough Notes Regarding "Time of Dan Button's", 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- "Same Sermon" by Harold Walker, CASBAH, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Samuel Gold vs. Pennsylvania RE: Felons Voting in Another State, 1959; 1966-1967; 1967; Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Sanitation, Sewage, and Water, 1961; Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Social Environment in Albany, 1961; 1963-1964; Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- South Mall Project, 1961-1962; Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Speeches, Notes, Correspondence of V. Lord, 1962; 1964; 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- State Investigation Commission, 1958-1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- State of NY Commission of Investigation (SIC) of Liberal Party Factional Dispute, 1984; Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Tax and Assessments Research, 1960-1961; 1965; 1971-1972; Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Tea Party Release, 1962; Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Unidentified Speeches and Notes, 1964; Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- The University of the State of New York, Albany, 1954; 1957-1958; 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Urban League, 1966; 1968-1969; Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Urban Renewal, 1958-1959; 1961; 1963; 1965; Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Voter Behavior/ Political Analyses, 1964; 1982-1983; Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Voter Contact Info by Ward, 1975; Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Voting/Voters, 1964; 1975; Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Welfare, 1964-1965; Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Welfare, Research, 1960-1961; Undated (Box 6, Folder 3)